Walter R. Ihrke Papers 1989.0082
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Walter R. Ihrke Papers
undated, 1925-1988
1989.0082
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
21.1 Linear feet
Walter Ihrke, a composer and musician, headed the music department at the University of Connecticut from 1949-1965. The collection contains scores and recordings as well as correspondence, publications and documentation of Ihrke's "Automated Musical Training" ["Ihrke Method"].
Ihrke, Walter R.
Biography
Walter R. Ihrke received bachelor of music degrees in organ, composition and piano from the Wisconsin Conservatory of Music, master of music degrees in composition and piano from the University of Michigan and a doctorate in composition from the Eastman School of Music ( Rochester, NY).
Throughout his career, Ihrke was active as a composer, organist and pianist, writing extensively for modern dance, piano, orchestra, band, voice and chorus. Prior to his appointment at UConn, Ihrke was the head of the music department at Mission House College ( WI) and taught at Stephens COllege ( MO and Peabody College ( TN).
In 1949, Dr. Ihrke was appointed head of the music department at the University of Connecticut, a position he held until 1965. He continued to teach until his retirement in 1974.
Dr. Ihrke died on 8 August 1992 at the age of 84.
Scope and Content
The collection contains scores and recordings as well as correspondence, publications and documentation of Ihrke's "Automated Musical Training" ["Ihrke Method"].
Arrangement
Series I: Inventory ( undated, 1925-1988 )
Acquisition Information
Dr. Ihrke donated the materials in several installments beginning in 1989.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Ihrke, Walter R.; University of Connecticut.; College teachers; Composers; Correspondence; Manuscripts (document genre); Music--Instruction and study; Notes; Publications; Scores; Sound recordings
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1925-1988
  - Concert programs, 1931-1974 (Box 1)
    - "Long Enough We Now Have Lived In This New Land...", University of Connecticut Symphony Orchestra and Choral Society, Jorgensen Auditorium - featuring "That Continent" (Ihrke), 1974 April 19
    - "Midwestern Mural", Orchesis, Stephens College [modern dance program partially composed by Ihrke], 1940 April 19
    - Collection of programs in which Dr. Ihrke performed, 1931-1960
  - Printed poems set by Ihrke, undated (Box 1)
  - Rresume, references, biographical information, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with administration at Universities of New Hampshire and Connecticut; Reed College; and B.F. Skinner of Harvard University, undated (Box 1)
  - Bibliography of publications, circa 1973 (Box 1)
  - Photograph--Automated Music Training system and use, circa 1967 (Box 1)
  - Photograph--Ihrke portraits, 1927, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Press comments, 1925-1970 (Box 1)
  - "Automated Music Training," The Journal of Research in Music Education, 11:1 (1963)/ Council for Research in Music Education, Bulletin No.2, 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Automated Music Training: Final Report on Phase One," The Journal of Research in Music Education, 14:4, 1971 (Box 1)
  - "A Modular Station for Automated Music Training," Educational Technology, 1971 Summer (Box 1)
  - "Music Literature as a Means of Integration,", 1952 (Box 1)
  - "Programming Principles in Automated Pitch Training," Council for Research in Music Education, Bulletin 29, 1972 (Box 1)
  - "Automated Music Training: Pitch Training Manual,", 1972 (Box 1)
  - Final Report, Grant No. OEG-1-71-0003 (509): "A Study of the Present State of Electronic Music Training, Including Computer-Assisted Instruction; A Bibliography,", undated (Box 1)
  - "That Continent [A Cantata for Chorus, soloists and orchestra]" - libretto (2), printed piano-vocal scores (3), piano-vocal score copy, bound piano-vocal score, orchestral parts, undated (Box 2)
  - "Ode and Scherzo for Concert Band" - bound score, 1955 (Box 3)
  - "Pageantry" - bound score, undated (Box 3)
  - "That Continent" - bound piano/vocal score, libretto, copies (orchestral parts, orchestral score), manuscript, bound orchestral score [torn and with revisions], 1957 (Box 3)
  - Concerto for Violin and Orchestra - copies (string parts, piano/violin reduction, violin score), bound copy (full score, piano reduction/violin reduction), printed parts, 1941, 1946 (Box 4)
  - "An Answer of Peace: A Dramatic Cantata" - libretto (2), text sketches, correspondence from librettist [Harold Belgum], chorus and soloist parts (manuscript), copy, manuscript (full score), bound score, 1938 (Box 5)
  - "Fugue by J.S. Bach [No. 5 in The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book II] for Woodwind Quintet" -- [score and parts], undated (Box 6)
  - "Fugue by J.S. Bach [in E Major] from The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book II] transcribed for Brass Quintet" -- [score, incomplete parts], undated (Box 6)
  - "How Long Wilt Thou Forget Me,", undated (Box 6)
  - "I Walk the Noisy Streets" -- copy, final manuscript, printed copies (2), undated (Box 6)
  - "My Love is Fair" - printed copies (6), undated (Box 6)
  - "Purcell Sonata [arr. for viola and piano]" - final manuscript (score and part), undated (Box 6)
  - Songs [contained in manuscript notebook and bound volumes] (Box 6)
    - "A Lullabye" - manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1932
    - "A Song of Thanksgiving" - sketches, final manuscript, negative, 1959
    - "A True Woman's-Eye" - manuscript, final manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, undated
    - "Cold Dawn" - final manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1930
    - "Dust Hangs Fragrant" - final manuscript, undated
    - "Gethsemane" - sketches, photocopy, bound copies (2), copy, 1964
    - "Heritage" - final manuscript, bound copy, copy, 1939
    - "I Walk the Noisy Streets" - manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1956
    - "My Love Is Fair" - bound copy, printed copy, copy, 1984
    - "Night" -- final manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1930
    - "Overture", 1945
    - "Song" - final manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1930
    - "Song of Thanksgiving" - bound copies (2), copy, 1959
    - "The Sun Worshipper" - final manuscript, printed copies (6), bound copies (2), copy, 1946
    - "[This] Romeo Stuff" - printed copy, final manuscript, bound copy, copy, undated
    - "To Music" - printed copy, final manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1931
    - "Tranquility" - manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1939
    - "Transcience" - manuscript, final manuscript, bound copies (2), copy, 1930
    - "Why Art Thou Silent?" - manuscripts (2), bound copies (2), copy, 1929
    - untitled ["now is my passion gone/ Receding night at dawn"] - partial printed copy, undated
  - "Suite for Cello and Piano" - sketches (form chart), manuscript, copy, bound copies (3), photocopies, 1983 (Box 6)
  - "Tragic Poem for cello and piano" - final manuscript, 1934 (Box 6)
  - Transcription for Orchestra: "O Mensch, bewein deine Sünde gross", J.S. Bach - final [score], 1934 (Box 6)
  - "The Hour Sinister: A Dramatic Ballet" - libretto, manuscript, bound copy, 1935 (Box 6)
  - "The Shadows of the Evening Hours" [title not marked - see Box 13], undated (Box 6)
  - "The Wind is Tapping" [for 3-part treble voices], published by Aeolian Choral Series (7), 1958 (Box 6)
  - Aria, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Suite for Cello and Piano, mvts. I and III, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Vinton B. Haas
    - Mr. and Mrs. Jerome M. Birdman
    - Rev. and Mrs. Rolland G. Ewing
    - Professor Abraham A. Schwadron
    - Ruth Dedrick
    - Dr. Nathan L. Dubin
  - The Connecticut Alumnus, 1983 November (Box 6)
  - Department of Music Convocation announcement [Suite for Cello & Piano], 1983 September (Box 6)
  - The Hartford Courant, 1983 August 31 (Box 6)
  - Notes and Lines [School of Fine Arts publication], 1984-1984 Winter (Box 6)
  - Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia Fraternity Province XIV Convention program, 1958 January (Box 6)
  - The University of Connecticut Chronicle, 3:1, 1983 Winter (Box 6)
  - Ballets (Box 7)
    - "Fire Festival - dramatic ballet in one act" - libretto by Robert B. Miller, 1935
    - "Fire Worship - Ballet for Two Pianos" [incomplete manuscript], 1935
    - "Pavane - a Ballet in Three Acts" - manuscript of piano score (2 volumes); copies (string instruments only), 1935
    - Three Dances from "Pavane": orchestral parts (final manuscripts), undated
    - "Processional" - libretto by Robert B. Miller, 1936
  - Concert Band (Box 8)
    - "Ode and Scherzo [for Concert Band]" - printed parts [wind, brass, percussion only], copy (score), final manuscript [all parts], undated
    - "Pageantry" - original manuscript score; copies [score and parts]; final manuscript [parts] with errata, 1956
    - Sketches for band works, including "Band Suite" and "Fantasy", undated
  - First Symphony - sketches, score, string parts, manuscript [1st and 3rd movements], bound score, printed parts, undated (Box 9)
  - Pslam for Wind Ensemble - scores and parts, undated (Box 10)
  - Works for solo piano, choir, or solo voice, undated (Box 11)
    - Compositions for Piano Solo - includes: Theme and Variations, Sonata, Prelude, "Melancholy", two Bagatelles, "Serenade to a Debutante", "Scapegoat", Etude, "Suite for Modern Dance"
    - Love in Seven Dimensions (libretto by Robert Miller)
    - Songs - includes: "Why Art Thou Silent", "Song", "Night", "Cold Dawn" "Transience", To Music", "A True Woman's-Eye", "Romeo Stuff", "A Lullabye", "Tranquility", "Heritage", "The Sung Worshipper", "I Walk the Noisy Streets", "Song of Thanksgiving", "Gethsemane", "My Love Is Fair"
    - "That Continent" (cantata, text by Paul Engle) [2]
  - Audio material (Box 12)
    - "Masters Series P. I - Pitch Training" (7), undated
    - "MS P. III" (5), undated
    - "MS I - Rhythm Training" (20), undated
    - "Montreal 11/66" [contains recordings through August 1967], 1966-1967
    - Tape threading leader (1), undated
    - Unmarked reels (4), undated
  - Anthems, various works, notebooks/sketches (Box 13)
    - 23rd Psalm [for women's chorus], bound copy, -copy, manuscripts, undated
    - Aria for Harp - sketches, loose and bound copies, correspondence, 1979
    - "As the Sun Doth Daily Rise [Anthem for Mixed Voices]" - manuscript, printed copy, undated
    - "Improvisation" [for piano] (draft and manuscript), undated
    - "Save Me, O God [Anthem - Psalm LIV]" - manuscript, undated
    - Sonata for Two Pianos, original manuscript, loose and bound copies, undated
    - String Quartet, score and parts, 1983
    - Suite for Cello and Piano - bound copy, undated
    - Suite for Modern Dance - bound copy and manuscript, undated
    - Theme and Variations - full manuscripts, 1926, 1928
    - "The Shadows of the Evening Hours" - manuscript, 1974
    - "The Ways" [unaccompanied mixed voices] - manuscript, loose and printed copies (5), 1959
    - "The White Brother" [manuscript, from "Suite for Modern Dance"], undated
    - Variation for 'Cello and Piano - piano score (5), cello part (4), loose and bound copies (score, cello part, 1987
  - Notebooks/sketches, undated (Box 13)
    - Various sketches, including "Improvisation", "Ritual Dance", undated
    - Original manuscript of "Tranquility", undated
    - Choral version of "Cold Dawn", undated
    - Sketches: "Dancer", "Miss You in the Rain", undated
    - Completed: "Heritage"; "Scapegoat", "White Brother"*, "Machine Age"* [*from "Suite for Modern Dance"], undated
    - "Diversions" - original full manuscript, undated
    - Sketches - Aria for Harp; "A Cheerful Overture"; Flute Quartet mvt. II, Overture (Wind Ensemble); Overture for Orchestra, Psalms mvts. III and IV, 1977-1982
    - "Improvisation" from Suite for Modern Dance - draft, 1935
    - "Lullabye" - original manuscript, 1935
    - Sketches (untitled), undated
    - Sketches: "Dance"; Psalms, "Rhythmic Overture"; "Fugue"; Psalm for Wind Ensemble; untitled song, undated, 1940-1981
    - Transcription of Prelude and Fugue in E minor, J.S. Bach (?), undated
  - "Material for choral works" [envelope]: includes Biblical verses, untitled poetry, text from Bugs Bunny and Punch & Judy, and poetry by F.R. Scott ("Poem called Overture" and Carol Wilson Link ("Songs for a Changing Voice"), undated (Box 13)
  - Audio recordings (Box 14)
    - "A-Side- Blank tape before the Couperin begins. About 5 minutes.", undated
    - "Cassette 4": Suite for Modern Dance, "Pageantry", Ode & Scherzo, "Legend", Overture, undated
    - "Cassette 24": "That Contrast"; Cantata, undated
    - Debussy: The Moonlit Terrace, Masques / Ihrke: Adagio and Scherzo mvts. from Piano Sonata, undated
    - Ihrke - Legend of the Night for Cello, Harp and Orchestra; Eastern Connecticut Symphony Orchestra; Victor Norman, conductor; Allyn Bayson, harp; Claudio Jaffe, cello, 1980
    - Ihrke Piano Program: Mendelssohn - Song Without Words; Schumann - Novellette; Brahms - Rhapsodie; Tcherepnin - Bagatelles 1-10; Prokofiev - Sarcasmes; Robert Palmer - Toccata Ostinato, 1957
    - Nocturne [for organ and piano], undated
    - Suite for Cello and Piano - Walter Ihrke, 1983
    - Suite for Cello and Piano/WTIC interview with Faith Middleton, undated
    - UConn SFA 20th Anniversary Interview, undated
    - Walter Ihrke - songs, undated
    - Walter Ihrke's Violin Concerto; Theodore Arm, Violinist, 1988 December 11; 1 audio cassette (28 min.): analog (Cassette 1989-0082/AC 1, Disk 1989-0082/CD1 R)
      Access
      Original not available due to fragility. Use 1989-0082/CD1 R.
    - Walter R. Ihrke - Overture for Orchestra, performed by Manchester Civic Orchestra; Jack Heller, conductor, 1979 April 8
  - Correspondence re: Nocturne for organ & piano, undated (Box 14)
  - "A Legend of the Night" (1939) - original manuscript, final score manuscript (2), orchestral parts, piano reduction (2), copy (Box 14)
  - "Diversions" for unaccompanied mixed chorus - original manuscript, copies, 1976-1977 (Box 14)
  - Nocturne for organ and piano - original manuscript; final manuscript; publisher's proofing copies; H.W. Gray edition, 1931, 1938, 1950 (Box 14)
  - Scherzo for Trumpet and Piano - loose and bound copies (4), undated (Box 14)
  - Lecture notes and materials from Music 192, 254, 256 356, undated (Box 15)
  - "Programming Principles in Automated Pitch Training", Ihrke, Council for Research in Music Education Bulletin, circa 1972 (Box 15)
  - Automated Music Training - "The Ihrke Method" (Box 15)
    - Copyrighted manuals, undated
    - Demonstration materials, undated
    - Machine schematics/diagrams, undated
    - Original manuscripts of Master Series I, Books 1 and 2 (programmed musical examples), undated
    - "Pitch Monitor" and "Rhythm Monitor" (Drs. Walter R. Ihrke and Elmer A. Ihrke, co-inventors) patent applications, disclosures and correspondence, circa 1969
    - Raw experimental data, undated
    - Release studies: Rhythm Training Manual [3], undated
  - Theory Teaching Manual" - original (1) and printed manuscripts (3), undated (Box 15)
  - "[Rhime of the] Ancient Mariner" [for mixed choir and orchestra] - sketches and original manuscript, 1934 (Box 16)
  - Ode and Scherzo [for wind ensemble] - copies of score and parts, 1955 (Box 16)
  - Orchestra for Overture - bound score (2), parts (printed and photocopied), copies of score and parts, 1978 (Box 16)
  - Automated Music Training (Box 17)
    - "MS II - keep" (19) [audio recordings], undated
    - File box containing musical [print] examples for Automated Music Training system, undated